Joe: The ‘Triad of impairments’ was
a breakthrough in its time as it
gave clarity to what had seemed to be
unrelated clinical phenomena and made
way for recognition of the different
levels of impairment, especially
‘high functioning’ forms of Autism.
The observation about the lack of
pretend play, a seemingly small
thing, had big consequences and
would have a lasting impact on
diagnostic and assessment methods.
Beth: However, for some, the ‘triad’
wasn’t perfect as it didn’t go far enough.
It didn’t cover sensory impairment, and
the problems individuals with Autism
have with light, sound and touch.
Previously, impairments needed to be
evident in the ‘triad’ in order for
a diagnosis of Autism to be made.
Joe: But as we have said before
there are always new ideas coming
forward and recently the well-known
‘triad of impairments’ is becoming
referred to as a ‘dyad of impairment’.
The ‘Dyad of impairment’ looks
to highlight all the specific
difficulties people with Autism
have, combining ‘social interaction’
and ‘communication and language’,
into ‘social communication’ skills.
Beth: And a key thing is where the
‘triad’ didn’t refer to the ‘sensory
needs’ of individuals with Autism, this
is now to be included in the ‘restricted
and repetitive behaviour’ sections.